Hi, this is John Stewart, and this is the different types of fire you can learn to build.
There's four different types of fire you can learn, and use them in different scenarios.
If you want to cook, the best fire for you is use the log cabin fire.
This is really good, because the log cabin fire is really ventilated, so it gets a lot of oxygen, which helps put off more heat, but most importantly is the logs freely fall on top of each other as they burn, and they make really, really good pieces of coal that put off really good heat, to where you can transfer them; put them on top of a Dutch oven, up under it in a different location.
Second type of fire is a tepee fire.
This is going to be great in case you are really cold.
Snowy climates this is good, because this puts really good heat off.
It concentrates the heat into the area right surrounding you; doesn't dissipate very really very fast, so the tepee fire, you just pile it up just like a Indian tepee, and let it burn, and it'll keep you really, really warm.
Third type of fire is going to be your lean-to fire.
This is when you have the big type, big log beside your fire pit, and you prop other limbs on this.
This is going to put off good heat, but it's also going to help light the area really well.
If your tent's on one side of the log, put your fire on that side, and that log will block the heat and the light, and it'll mainly force it towards your side of the campground to where you light your area really well.
And you just want to keep piling wood on this so it burns really, really bright, and always has a tall flame.
And the fourth type of fire you can build is a signaling fire.
With a signaling fire you want to sort of combine your log cabin and your tepee.
This is so you have a really big base, and it burns really bright, and that you have an area that you can throw stuff on top of to make your signaling.
And this is how you can demonstrate different types of fire.